<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Julian Barg</title>
    <link>https://www.jbarg.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.jbarg.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Julian Barg's website. See what I am up to. Also, exposition of my past work.
</description>
    <generator>Distill</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Pipelines &amp; expropriation</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-22-pipelines-expropriation</link>
      <description>I don't like the term "eminent domain". It is clearly a euphemism. [Here is another story about expropriation in the US](https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/apr/22/byhalia-pipeline-memphis-black-landowners). Sure, the US will never date nationalize your company or put any significant tax on your riches--but they will take it for the benefit of corporate profits. What great progress. The usual modus operandi for the construction of pipelines, as with many public works in the US, poses a justice issue: like with highways in the mid-century, property value are a factor for deciding where to build pipelines. Guess which neighborhoods are usually poorer and have their propert value assessed at a lower level? So African-Americans, who are already disadvantaged, have a harder time building up any wealth because if they buy real estate at lower value in an African-American neighborhood do not get the same returns on their investments that the European immigrants get. Chances are, they will even lose a significant share of their money. I remember reading a great article written in first person on "redlining" and "black homeownership" in present times, cannot find it anymore. But google shows that there are many interesting reads around on that.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-22-pipelines-expropriation</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDT is back, baby!</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-13-ddt-is-back-baby</link>
      <description>Silent Spring by Rachel Carson is a classic. DDT may be the most famous toxic pesticide out there. Where did DDT go after it was banned? [Turns out, straight into the ocean.](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aGWgg4rem5s) Hundreds of thousands of barrels. Great choice!</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-13-ddt-is-back-baby</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oil &amp; Gas discourse in one swift article</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-13-oil-gas-discourse-in-one-swift-article</link>
      <description>The fantastic Emily Atkin over at Heated managed to [summarize the whole discourse on climate change between the oil industry and activists in one swift article](https://heated.world/p/mike-rowe-oilsplainer). Mike Rowe, television host of *Dirty Jobs* gets sponsored by the API to make a show about history--cynically titled *Six Degrees*. Shout outs to the oil and gas industry galore. Not only that, but he will gladly defend his connection to the industry on Facebook--writing 6,000 words, free of charge to the API presumably. I believe Emily Atkin hits the nail on the head when she observes that this is not a guy selling out his believes--this is a guy who genuinly beliefs what he is saying. A far more weighty observation. Here is my take on this. He has made a show called *Dirty Jobs*. The implication is that "it's a dirty job and somebody has got to do it." "It ain't pretty, but we need it." Do we though? It seems he genuinly beliefs it, and he thinks those who disagree with him are naive. Is it naive to envision an alternative future though? In my opinion its not, it is far more naive and unimaginative to see the reality we live in as inevitable. *Alternativlos*--without alternatives--as we say in German. Few things are, but a lot of people want to tell us that it is. That's lazy thinking.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-13-oil-gas-discourse-in-one-swift-article</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qualitative data analysis</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-12-qualitative-data-analysis</link>
      <description>Today I have been looking at software for qualitative data analysis, and it is quite disappointing. The feature set that I would be hoping for of course is quite extensive, that is probably part of the reason. It should be (1) FOSS, (2) actively being developed, (3) available on Windows, macOS, Linux, (5) able to import text documents, PDFs, and ideally html files, (6) capable of importing highlights and notes from PDFs, (7) save its data in a convenient form, for instance as an SQL database. But it seems outside of Atlas Ti and NVivo there isn't much going on.

RQDA is really janky, but at least it saves its data as an SQLite database. QDAP only works with text data. Cassandre's website looks... sketchy... Of course Atlas Ti uses SPSS under the hood, which only makes sense if you are being developed by the same software (just a guess, I don't actually know). And it cannot import websites, only if you have already saved them to PDF. And NVivo straight up doesn't have a Linux client (you could probably run it in wine, but that's not the pont) AND requires NVivo to be installed on your system for you to be able to launch its browser version. What a dumpster fire. 

So the way I see it, you can do two things. Either organize your material yourself, but I think getting all the crossreferences into a discourse would not be feasible without taking way too much effort. Or you can think short term and run a project on Atlas Ti. I am sure they won't be at the top of the pack in ten years, so that's a pity. Won't be able to migrate your data out, either. I am now trying to organize as much as possible outside of software, before importing stuff as the last step. But the fact that you cannot even import the annotations that are already saved to a PDF document--so annoying.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-12-qualitative-data-analysis</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pollution from chemical weapons</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-10-chemical-weapons-pollution</link>
      <description>[Interesting article in the Smithsonian Magazine on the US army's handling of chemical weapons during the cold war.](https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/how-death-6000-sheep-spurred-american-debate-chemical-weapons-cold-war-180968717/) Reading this and looking at the map of US superfund sites, I can really imagine how that came to be.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-10-chemical-weapons-pollution</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why this blog?</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-10-why-this-blog</link>
      <description>When I started writing things down here, I had a vision in mind. Short notes, writen almost in a train of thought fashion. I come across interesting tidbits frequently, and I sometimes go back to some of them randomly. Obviously, I could just create a list, but that doesn't really correspond to my structure of thinking so to say. A blog seemed like a more intuitive tool to use. Last week I was thinking that it would be easier to just collect links and post them once a week. That kind of fails, because I never got to the "once a week" part. That's where the second benefit of this style of blog that I am aiming for comes in. Writing a note should only take me five minutes--then it is something I can do 2-3 times throuhout the day. Any polishing and it is going to throw my day off to much. Writing a post is also a great day to get the day started--knock something out right away. Hope I will get to enjoy doing that the next couple of days. Here goes for more productive blogging this week!</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-10-why-this-blog</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keystone spill without media coverage</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-02-keystone-spill-without-media-coverage</link>
      <description>Today while looking at some PHMSA data, I came across a curious bit of information. Apparently there has been a spill at the Keystone Pipeline Lucas station in Beaumont, Jefferson county, Tx. I was not able to find any newsreport on this spill, so here some basic information. The spill was discovered on May 7, 2020 by am employee conducting a routine inspection--NOT by the fancy newfangled real-time monitoring system (SCADA) that was also up and running at the time. A total of 442 barrels was spilled, and some had run off the facility by the time the spill was discovered. The spill was caused by a corroded pipe. Fortunately, the station was shut down at the time of the incident, or a lot more crude oil might have leaked. For more information, see PHMSA report number 20200166.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-04-02-keystone-spill-without-media-coverage</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maguire &amp; Hardy (2009</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-30-maguire-hardy-2009</link>
      <description>I took an in-depth look at Maguire &amp; Hard (2009) today. Great read. See my critical summary here: http://wiki.jbarg.net/Maguire%20&amp;%20Hardy%202009</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-30-maguire-hardy-2009</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>'Privatized police force' harassing activists on behalf of Enbridge</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-18-privatized-police-force</link>
      <description>[A water warrior claiming to be harassed by Minnesota police on behalf of Enbridge](https://heated.world/p/i-dont-feel-safe-here). Police officers trailing activists en route to protests for hours and billing Enbridge for the time. The original intention of the law that this is based on might have been to shift costs from the state to Embridge. The interesting question is whether Enbridge told the police to go all-out or whether police offices took the initiative and what we observe is a revenue-generating strategy by the police forces. My sense is that it did not require much communication for this situation to occur if Enbridge and the police are on the same page on this issue anyways. Another aspect: the first example in the text is a woman getting fined for failing to signal more than 100 feet before a turn. That police strategy we have all seen before: pull over a member of a group that you don't like--if you know the law well enough you will always be able to fine that individual for some obscure infraction. There are also lots of instances of use of excessive force of male police officers against female activists.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-18-privatized-police-force</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A different take on America</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-a-different-take-on-america</link>
      <description>[Well this is certainly a different take](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aNghg1Y-WIc). I think it's not just my own perception that America is far from where it was ten years ago, when it was still the undisputed "greatest country in the world". Looks like the Gravel Institute was founded to counter the infamous alt-right Prager U. The video certainly provides an interesting take. Taxes are higher in the US than elsewhere if local fees an health insurance is included. And the health system is of course abysmal, as the last couple of months have shown.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-a-different-take-on-america</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ALEC criminalizing protests</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-alec-criminalizing-protests</link>
      <description>[It seems that ALEC still is not done with criminalizing environmental protests](https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/fossil-fuel-protest_n_602c1ff6c5b6c95056f3f6af). Four new states might introduce the legislations that ALEC has shopped around, which would make it illegal to trespass on "critical infrastructure"--which of course includes pipelines. 

That creates a problem because, well, you cannot see a pipeline that is burried underground. The article has a lovely example. Approach some workers and cross an invisible line between public land and a construction site--and you will be arrested.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-alec-criminalizing-protests</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fossil fuel subsidies</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-fossil-fuel-subsidies</link>
      <description>[Looks like we will hear a lot more about fossil fuel subsidies](https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/katie-porter-big-oil-exec_n_6048243fc5b6cf72d0929289). From the "right side" of the issue.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-fossil-fuel-subsidies</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localized approach</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-localized-approach</link>
      <description>[Here an interesting vision of what sustainability can also look like](https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2021/mar/10/study-highlights-under-the-radar-uk-community-projects-green-benefits). The idea is to focus on local initiatives.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-localized-approach</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Texas, winter storm &amp; chemical industry</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-texas-winter-storm-chemical-industry</link>
      <description>A, classic! There was a little bit of a winter storm in Texas recently, remember? The one that knocked out electricity for most of the population. Well, guess what is also in Texas. Most of America's chemical industry. Because it is an attractive place for the chemical industry to be, where you can have your [chemical plants](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Fertilizer_Company_explosion) [blow](https://www.npr.org/2019/11/27/783263942/massive-explosion-rips-through-texas-chemical-plant) [up](https://www.nbcnews.com/storyline/hurricane-harvey/harvey-danger-how-toxic-air-texas-chemical-plant-explosion-n797876) [without](https://www.reuters.com/article/us-chemicals-fire-tpc-portneches-idUSKBN1Y80HH) [significant](https://www.cnn.com/2014/04/22/us/west-texas-fertilizer-plant-explosion-investigation) [repercussions](https://www.texastribune.org/2018/03/30/arkema-disaster-harvey-regulations-texas-crosby/). The EPA there is a toothless tiger: it will help you clean up and communicate with the public that they are safe, but they do not actually have the resources--or legislation--in place to prosecute the perpetrators.

The problem with having the chemical industry concentrated there is that the world is facing a [shortage](https://www.chemistryworld.com/news/polar-storm-paralyses-us-gulf-coast-petrochemical-sector/4013306.article) in [certain plastics](https://www.chemistryworld.com/news/polar-storm-paralyses-us-gulf-coast-petrochemical-sector/4013306.article). Not that I am a fan of plastics in the first place, but I do appreciate the irony. Lax regulations have led to the location of much of the chemical industry in Texas, a weak preparation of said plants for disasters, and to the devastating blackouts. Something, something, economically unsustainable etc.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-17-texas-winter-storm-chemical-industry</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Climat change is cancelled!</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-climat-change-is-cancelled</link>
      <description>Cancel culture? How about [Donald Trump trying to cancel climate change data](https://www.theverge.com/22313763/scientists-climate-change-data-rescue-donald-trump).</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-climat-change-is-cancelled</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covid close and personal</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-covid-close-and-personal</link>
      <description>I think one reason for the American schism on covid is the lack of "human-interest stories" on covid, for the lack of a better term. I saw a lot of reports on the lockdown, people "suffering" from the mask mandate, etc. But relatively little on people suffering from covid, the doctors, nurses, etc. There is one new relevant documentary from the times accessible [here](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M5BhuzqeDRU). It's probably not easy getting into a covid wing like that with your camera, so I appreciate the effort. And I also appreciate the perspective of what its like to battle covid in a less affluent community. Great stuff!

**Edit**: I forgot to mention, I am somewhat sure that one reason for the dearth of more personal covid content is Youtube's restrictive policy. I remember at least a handfull of creators mentioning that merely saying the c-word can lead to their video being demonitized. I understand that the policy was put in place to tackle desinformation, but it would be interesting to see in how far it has also done a bit of the opposite. My intuitition is that a nurse or patient suffering from covid would go either to youtube or to twitter to document their fate or make a plea to others. Now the only way to get on youtube and reach a sizable audience is to have an official news team by your side. Of course there is also the fact that many of the sickest cannot talk or comment on their fate at all.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-covid-close-and-personal</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gulf stream</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-gulf-stream</link>
      <description>A weakening gulf stream has been a convern in Europe for a number of years, one that is not talked about a lot in American media. The gulf stream is what makes for such mild weather in Europe, so it's kind of a big deal. [Now we see new negative records.](https://www.livescience.com/gulf-stream-slowing-climate-change.html) That's more than a  bit concerning. Not only would it mean colder winters in Europe, but also more extreme weather on both sides of the Atlantic (think hurricane season).</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-gulf-stream</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sublime text on new machines</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-sublime-text-on-new-machines</link>
      <description>As you may know, I do have a bit of an obsession with IDEs, especially free and/or open source software. I have ignored sublime text for a couple of years but finally came around to it. And now I have finally discovered my favorite feature of it. To install packages in sublime--and the packages are really the killer feature--you first need to install thepackage manager. Turns out, [if you place the package manager file in the sublime folder, sublime will install the package manager automatically on startup.](https://stackoverflow.com/a/19531651/8963109) And then you can also place a file with your installed packages in the settings folder, and sublime will install these for you too. Why this matters? It means you can set up a new machine with something like ansible, for instance installing sublime with apt, and then a simply get all your options with curl, and your machine is ready to go, but also has everything installed from scratch.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-08-sublime-text-on-new-machines</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facebook's worst ad ever</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-facebooks-worst-ad-ever</link>
      <description>Not related to what I am usually interested in, but still. [Facebook's ad that wants to convince you to opt into tracking on iOS.](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eRABUy6G2GY) God. I don't know why it gives me such creepy vibes. The music. The visuals. The 1984-esque message. What a terrible ad.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-facebooks-worst-ad-ever</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freshwater fish under threat</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-freshwater-fish-under-threat</link>
      <description>We have heard a lot about the oceans being under threat. There is the warming climate, and runoffs, we witnessed a terrifying bleaching event at the Great Barrier Reef, an algea bloom off the cost of Florida, and a [Starfishes literally "dissolving"](https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-31-starfish-extinction-event/). But many rivers are also under threat, and [now WWF has summarized how bad things are for freshwater fishes](https://www.cbsnews.com/news/freshwater-fish-catastrophic-extinction-endangered-species-climate-change/). The answer: very.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-freshwater-fish-under-threat</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>German forest 'dying'</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-german-forest-dying</link>
      <description>That's probably a topic that most outside of Germany are not familiar with, but Germans really care about the forest. What forests don't like are high temperatures, droughts, and extreme weather. All of which we had plenty of in the recent past. So maybe its not all that surprising that the German forest is in a really bad shape. So bad that [German Spiegel writes that the German forest is "dying"](https://www.spiegel.de/wissenschaft/natur/wald-in-deutschland-noch-nie-sind-so-viele-baeume-gestorben-wie-2020-a-5233254c-b79e-4f8e-83c3-de50b2349ef4). Only 21% of trees have an undamaged crown, the lowest number ever recorded. A surprising cause of this decline: monoculture. Many of Germany's forests aren't all that natural. They have been created, e.g., to serve the early mining industry many centuries ago. And of course for that purpose (or whatever other purpose) you would only plant whatever kind of tree serves you best. So bark beetles are having a blast right now.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-german-forest-dying</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Texas blackout</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-texas-blackout</link>
      <description>[Great video at Climate Town last week](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PmYvkCXXI4E). Texas experienced power outages, related to extreme weather. The power grid, all sorts of power plants, all struggling, but that is apparently not what Fox told its viewers--they blamed it on renewables. Anyways, the Texas blackout was an interesting episode of climate change. As a reminder: climate change means that our climate does not just become warmer on average, but the variance of our weather also increases. In this case, something about the [polar vortex having become unstable or "wobbly" and leaving its semi-permanent home, the arctic](https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/texas-power-outage-underscores-looming-climate-tests/).
(cont.)</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-texas-blackout</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>US flood risk</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-us-flood-risk</link>
      <description>The US is getting flooded. A lot. [And the price for flood insurance is going up.](https://www.npr.org/2021/02/22/966428165/a-looming-disaster-new-data-reveal-where-flood-damage-is-an-existential-threat) Paradoxically, that may be a good thing. Flood insurances are subsidiced, and the price of the insurance is not based on the price of the house. In other words, rich folks benefit a lot from the subsidies. Just like those beautiful Miami beaches are always gonna be taken care of by the government. Also, it is just a terrible use of resources. Crappy houses are rebuilt again and again. And dams galore.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-us-flood-risk</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volkswagen vs. local emissions regulation</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-volkswagen-vs-local-emissions-regulation</link>
      <description>(So now it's Volkswagen's turn to stand up against emissions regulation)[https://www.wsj.com/articles/volkswagen-asks-supreme-court-to-block-local-emissions-regulations-11611694514]. It would be really convenient for them if only state level in the US and up could do emissions regulations, wouldn't it? Why is this such as throwback? [Climate Town has a video on GM fighting regulations that would have mandated EVs on the road--in the 90s!](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RNvvvVt_628)</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-03-07-volkswagen-vs-local-emissions-regulation</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starfish extinction event</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-31-starfish-extinction-event</link>
      <description>Not exactly on top of the news, but still important: [There was/is a starfish mass extinction event going on since 2013, with starfishes seemingly "dissolving".](https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/18/science/sea-stars-genes.html) Now [researchers](https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2020.610009) have found a likely explanation: [microbial activity under conditions of overfertilization](https://www.spektrum.de/news/bakterien-und-ueberduengung-lassen-seesterne-zu-schleim-werden/1822031). It wouldn't be the first case of fertilizer runoff causing terrifying events. [I hope everybody remembers the toxic algea bloom off the coast of Florida.](https://www.tampabay.com/news/environment/2020/06/08/why-floridas-toxic-algae-crisis-is-worse-than-people-realize/)</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-31-starfish-extinction-event</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brexit negotiations--the full story</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-22-brexit-full-story-negotiations</link>
      <description>[The FT has written a big tell-all about the Brexit negotiations.](https://www.ft.com/content/cc6b0d9a-d8cc-4ddb-8c57-726df018c10e) It's getting quite clear that Boris Johnson has traded everything--EVERYTHING!--he had on the table for sovereignty. Sovereignty as the highest priority. Higher than anything else. "The process just wasn’t driven by thinking about what the UK really wanted from a deal, but to justify the claims to sovereignty. It was quite astonishing" says one government official. (cont.)</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-22-brexit-full-story-negotiations</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keystone XL</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-19-keystone-xl</link>
      <description>[So it looks like Biden is planning to scrap Keystone XL on day one](https://www.politico.com/news/2021/01/17/biden-yank-keystone-pipeline-permit-460142). One the one hand obviously great news. On the other hand, it shows again what the whole ordeal had already proven so far. Whether or not a pipeline is constructed is not a process that is decided by scientific considerations. It depends mostly on political will. A funny side note is that TC Energy tried to preempt that move by announcing on Sunday that the pipeline would achieve net-zero emissions "across operations". Well, the emissions of **operating** a pipeline is not what we are concerned about...</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-19-keystone-xl</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flaws in legal theory</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-flaws-in-legal-theory</link>
      <description>[The tether story](https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-tether-defrauding-everybody/) reminded me a bit of Trump's legal strategy. The goal is not to win, but to gain more time. In the meantime, Trump could collect donations to "challenge the vote" (pay off campaign debts), or he could implement policy that--even if later reverted--could have a long-lasting impact. I think this strategy poses an enormous challenge to legal theory: justice will not be done if bad faith actors game the court system. Maybe in the end they lose a legal fight--in the meantim they have already "created facts". How does this relate to my work? The natural environment is truly the most vulnerable actor in this game. Who cares whether you lose the legal fight on the building permit if you have already built the pipeline? The damage to the natural environment cannot be undone.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-flaws-in-legal-theory</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How is Brexit going?</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-how-is-brexit-going</link>
      <description>[Very level-headed and comprehensive article of the Irish Raidió Teilifís Éireann on Brexit.](https://www.rte.ie/news/2021/0115/1190108-brexit-analysis-and-comment/) Refreshing after two weeks of "Netherlands stole my sandwich" type journalism.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-how-is-brexit-going</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tether defrauding everybody</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-tether-defrauding-everybody</link>
      <description>[This is genius and I love it](https://crypto-anonymous-2021.medium.com/the-bit-short-inside-cryptos-doomsday-machine-f8dcf78a64d3) (inasmuch much as you can love fraud). How to defraud crypto investors these days? Create a currency that you claim is pegged to the dollar (but never actually show you hold the assets). Then use it to buy as much cryptocurrency as you like. Step 3: profit!!! :)

**Edit**: it is basically a ponzi scheme that would make Madoff proud.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-tether-defrauding-everybody</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The tragedy of renewable energy</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-the-tragedy-of-renewable-energy</link>
      <description>Renewable energy is as close to "infinite energy" as we will ever get. Why aren't we building a utopia already?</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-16-the-tragedy-of-renewable-energy</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solar 'cheapest electricity in history'</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-10-solar-cheapest-electricity-in-history</link>
      <description>Quick announcement by the IEA--[solar energy is now the cheapest energy in history](https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2020/10/solar-cheap-energy-coal-gas-renewables-climate-change-environment-sustainability). The announcement certainly marks a significant turn for the IEA. But it will probably not come as a surprise to those of you who have watched solar power mature. I think the trajectory was there for a number of years. I remember the resistance against renewable energy veiling itself in a dress of economics, but in retrospect it seems incredible how little forward looking that resistance was, even in economic terms.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-10-solar-cheapest-electricity-in-history</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Take emission certificates off the market</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-10-take-emission-certificates-off-the-market</link>
      <description>Today I was thinking to myself 'emission certificates on the EU ETS seem pretty cheap, we could just buy those in heaps to force the prices to go up'. So I did a little bit of digging around and found [the great _Compensators*_ project](https://www.compensators.org/en/compensate-2/) by the even more amazing _Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research_ (PIK). Their website makes it pretty easy to buy emission certificates, either by unit or by price, any fraction possible. At currently 41.52€, still a steal. Although I still remember prices being in the 20s. Well, prices going up is a good thing in this case I suppose.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-10-take-emission-certificates-off-the-market</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The case for climate change mitigation through societal transformation</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-04-the-case-for-climate-change-mitigation-through-societal-transformation</link>
      <description>[The Heinrich Böll foundation makes the case for tackling climate change by our society adopting a different lifestyle, e.g., by relying less on cars, eating less meat, and traveling by train rather than plane.](https://konzeptwerk-neue-oekonomie.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/A%20Societal%20Transformation%20Scenario.pdf) I believe that quality of life is determined more by how we spend our time and whether we create meaningful memories, rather than a high GDP, big cars, and big houses, so this report certainly strikes a nerve with me. The most important point though is certainly that we should not assume or hope that technological change will in the future make our current lifestyle more sustainable. I do not see the value in trying to preserve everything *as-is*.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2021-01-04-the-case-for-climate-change-mitigation-through-societal-transformation</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who are climate change deniers?</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-27-who-are-climate-change-deniers</link>
      <description>[Interesting video by CNBC on climate change deniers](https://youtu.be/f1rxv1yPQrc). On the one hand, the video highlights some of the money flows to climate change denying think tanks. On the other hand Jerry Taylor of the Niskanen Center says in the video: "[...] everyone that I knew back when I was a climate skeptic were honestly persuaded that climate change was a wildly overblown concern that is being used by the left to destroy Western capitalism. This [...] explains more of the right's hostility to climate action than a naked story of enjoying checks being cut by the American Petroleum Institute" ([time stamp: 5:54](https://youtu.be/f1rxv1yPQrc?t=354)). For context, Jerry Taylor started his career about three decades ago at the American Legislative Exchange Council (ALEC), which today has gained infamy for [shopping around anti-protest legislation](https://www.propublica.org/article/how-louisiana-lawmakers-stop-residents-efforts-to-fight-big-oil-and-gas), [with great success](https://www.icnl.org/usprotestlawtracker/)! Jerry Taylor spent 23 years at the Koch-funded Cato Institute before joining the other side of the aisle and founding the Niskanen Center to lobby for a market-based solution of climate change.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-27-who-are-climate-change-deniers</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some organizational insights into the Russian security aparatus</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-23-some-organizational-insights-into-the-russian-security-aparatus</link>
      <description>With everything happening in the US, it's easy for what happens in the rest of the world to get burried. So I am glad that I did not skip over [this video by Alexei Navalny where he calls the FSB agents that just a few weeks ago attempted to murder him--and one of them actually answers](https://youtu.be/ibqiet6Bg38). Some interesting insights into how Russian security is organized.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-23-some-organizational-insights-into-the-russian-security-aparatus</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence-based surgery?</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-20-evidence-based-surgery</link>
      <description>An [interesting talk by Ian Harris of the University of Sydney](https://youtu.be/jF3d059QBkM) that explains why the scientific method does not always drive whether we receive surgery or not. An interesting example of an area I would have expected to be completely evidence based that is sometimes much more grounded in tradition.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-20-evidence-based-surgery</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Responsible research Vision 2030 position paper</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-20-responsible-research-vision-2030-position-paper</link>
      <description>For anybody who has not come across the [Vision 2030 position paper by Anne Tsui, Jerry Davis, etc.](https://rrbm.network/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Position-Paper_revised_8April2020.pdf) yet, read it! In brief, they advocate for reproducible research on relevant issues, in service of society.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-20-responsible-research-vision-2030-position-paper</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recycling</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-19-recycling</link>
      <description>If you haven't seen this [video](https://youtu.be/PJnJ8mK3Q3g) on the issues with recycling, you should probably watch it right now. In a similar vain, [this article](https://www.npr.org/2020/09/11/897692090/how-big-oil-misled-the-public-into-believing-plastic-would-be-recycled) by NPR on the topic. In short, the plastics industry created an identifier logo for different plastics that looks very similar to the public domain recycling logo, and then lobbied for legislation to make that logo mandatory on all public products. The result: the public beliefs that our plastics are recycled, when really only 10% of them are (at least in the US).</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-19-recycling</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global warming experiment</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-18-global-warming-experiment</link>
      <description>I was looking around for practical experiments that demonstrate global warming, and found [this wonderful short experiment by NASA](https://web.archive.org/web/20161118141122/https://glory.gsfc.nasa.gov/globalwarmingexperiment.html).</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-18-global-warming-experiment</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ontology</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-18-ontology</link>
      <description>If you are like me, or everybody I know, you mix up ontology and epistemology on a regular basis. Well, legendary Aussie psychadelic rock band King Gizzard and the Lizzard Wizzard decided to chima in and write a song about [Ontology](https://youtu.be/D5q5OEho8II). So you can listen to that and still not understand what ontology is about, isn't that great?</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-18-ontology</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new school of environmental economics?</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-17-new-school-of-environmental-economics</link>
      <description>Not entirely by chance did I come across this interesting discourse in economics about gas emissions. @Shapiro2018a have disaggregated CO, NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, PM10, PM2.5, SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, NO&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;, VOCs, and CO&lt;sub2&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; emission in the US from 1990-2008 by industry, location, facility, and product. They find that during that time period, emission reductions are driven not by technological change or trade, but by more stringent regulations. The cost of complying with these regulations in 2008 amounted to an implicit pollution tax equal to ~1.1% of total production cost--double the value in the year 1990. (cont.)</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-17-new-school-of-environmental-economics</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using new software</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-15-using-new-software</link>
      <description>The last couple of days I have started experimenting with distill, and began integrating it into my workflow--this blog is a result of that effort. The problem with using new software is that a lot of the features I desire are not there yet. In this case, I got a little bit too impatient maybe and went on github to report issues, and make feature requests. Since resources are limited, a lot of my reports have not been picked up yet, but one was. Being an early adapter is always a challenge, and reporting issues is part of that. On the one hand, I don't want to ask too much from open source developers. On the other hand, feedback from early adapters is what open source developers need in order to know in what direction to go. So it's some neat feedback for me to see that one of my reported issues became part of the (milestone 1.2 for R distill)[https://github.com/rstudio/distill/milestone/2]. I hope as a user I am contributing by reporting issues, and not just being a pain for the developers.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-15-using-new-software</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fierce resistance cannot prevent pipeline project</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-14-fierce-resistance-cannot-prevent-pipeline-project</link>
      <description>[Interesting report in the Boston Globe about the construction of a compressor station](https://www.bostonglobe.com/2020/12/12/metro/was-it-ever-fair-fight/). Massachusetts governor Charlie Baker was determined to approve the project, it seems. This story raises the question of what factors determine whether a pipeline project is approved. Since their 1999 policy revision, [FERC has approved 400 applications for pipeline projects, and has rejected only 2](https://www.analysisgroup.com/uploadedfiles/content/insights/publishing/ag_ferc_natural_gas_pipeline_certification.pdf). There are public input opportunities built into the certification process, but in practice these only serve to "inform" the public of a decision that has already been made.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-14-fierce-resistance-cannot-prevent-pipeline-project</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vaccine logistics</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-08-covid-logistics</link>
      <description>Why do countries need logistics partners to distribute the new vaccines? [Bloomberg has a pretty cool infographic](https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2020-uk-vaccine-logistics/). Shipping a few vials is fine, shipping literally millions is going to be quite the challenge.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/2020-12-08-covid-logistics</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to Jules website</title>
      <dc:creator>Julian Barg</dc:creator>
      <link>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/welcome</link>
      <description>Welcome to my website.</description>
      <guid>https://www.jbarg.net/posts/welcome</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
